Guide to the Albert Leon Guerard Papers, 1908-1960
Department of Special Collections
Guérard, Albert Léon. Papers,
1908-1960
M0957
Guérard, Albert Léon.
2.75 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Albert J. Guerard, 1983, 1997 and 1999.
Biography
Frenchman Albert Léon Guérard (1880-1959) spent most of his life as an American academic, and his work reflects an engagement with both France and the United States. Guérard came to the United States from France in 1906 to teach at Williams College. He taught at Stanford University from 1907 until his retirement in 1946, except for 12 years between 1913-1935 when he was at Rice University and served in the war. He was the author of numerous books and articles on French history and intellectual life.
Scope and Content
Collection contains many of ALG's original articles and monographs, both manuscripts and reprints. Materials include: works on the history and culture of France, correspondence and writings on urban planning in France and in the San Francisco Bay Area, and book reviews. Unpublished manuscripts found in this collection include PROBLEMS OF THE GREAT WAR (c1915), TRENDS IN CONTEMPORARY LITERATURE (1929), L'AVENIR DE PARIS (1958-59) and FRANCE BETWEEN THE TWO WORLD WARS (c1944). In addition there is biographical material, a bibliography, commencement addresses, reviews of his works, and an incomplete typescript of EPAVES, nd.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Guâerard, Albert Lâeon.; City planning--France.; City planning--California.; France--History.; Language, Universal.
Collection Contents
- Series I: Articles on Diverse Subjects - most unpublished
  - 5 articles, offprints: (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - - "Paris a hundred years ago, a study in perspective."
    - - "A Programme of Constructive Pacifism" in Proceedings of the Louisiana Teachers' Assoc.
    - - "Thomas Mann und unsere Zeit." In German.
    - - "Humanities and the Social Sciences."
    - - Prof. P.M.S. Vlackett, FRS. "The Problem of the Underdeveloped Countries." Annual Memorial Lecture at David Davies Memorial Institute of International Studies, Nov. 1959
  - "A Jewish National Home in Palestine." Typed MS. 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "urbanisme parisien - Servitude de Beauté." Carbon of typed MS. In French. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "To My African Friends." Typed MS. Published in Atlantic Monthly, 205 (Feb. 1960). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Comparative Literature?" Typed MS. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "'Excellence' in Education?" Typed MS. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Quest of Excellence - A Humanistic Utopia." Typed MS. Published in American Scholar, 29:1 (1959-60). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Millennia." Typed MS. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "To My Unknown Friends in India." Typed MS. Published in Aryan Path, 29:2 (Feb. 1958). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 5 short political pieces, all typed MS: (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - - "The Tribune of the People"
    - - "Quelques Suggestions pour l'application éventuelle à l'Allemagne de l'engageante formulé d'A.L. Guérard: "Ballots, not Bullets."
    - - "Gleichbrechtigung" Sauce for the French Goose and the German Gander: or: Disruption before Union."
    - - Letter to League of Nations William Allen White Committee 25 May 1940
    - - "An Ethical testament (Personality)
  - -"Testament to a Humanist." ALG Lecture at 1953 Brandeis Univ. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Work in Progress" folder. Notes, Poetry, ALG's bibliography. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Work in Progress" folder. "Golden Wedding." (Ideas developed in "Testament of a Liberal"). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Work in Progress" folder. Writings on religion; nationalism; "Fossils and Presences;" letter to Mr. Carey Williams, editor of the Nation; decadence; "My Legacy to Paris," article published in Holiday (March 1960?). (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - File on Religion, including long statement (1919);"Bottle in the Sea" (16 Feb. 1940); "Menorah Address" before the Rice Institute Menorah Society, 29 Nov. 1915. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence on Problems of the Great War. 1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - -press clipping and 5 pieces of correspondence with publisher, T. Fisher Unwin, largely about the book's being accepted for publication, and then "killed by British Censorship."
  - Problems of the Great War (Accepted, Announced, and Killed by British Censorship). Typed MS, only one in existence. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Trends in Contemporary Literature. Typed MS. "Interesting 'historic document.' How things looked about 1929." -AJG 11/26/85 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: France
  - Correspondence re: 1958 L'Avenir de Paris. 1957-59 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - L'Avenir de Paris. Typed original MS of 1959 work, only existing copy. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - France Between the Two World Wars. Typed MS, c1944 73 pages. Unpublished. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lands and Peoples: France. Typed MS, 88 pages. Unpublished. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Essays written for France-Amerique. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Essays written for France-Amerique. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Essays written for France-Amerique. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series III: City Planning
  - City Planning: Paris. English Essays. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - - "Paris and the River Seine"
    - - "Paris a Hundred Years Ago (1854-55) -A Study in Perspective."
    - - "The Paris World Fairs 1855-1937." 16 May 1949
    - - "Paris Yesterday and Tomorrow" offprint copy from Journal of the American Institute of Planners. Vol. XIX, No. 1 (Winter 1953).
    - - "The Rebuilding of French Cities." 17 Dec. 1958
  - City Planning: Paris. English Essays. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - -"Paris" article for the World Book Encyclopedia.
    - -3 pages of notes.
  - City Planning: Paris. English Essays. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - - "The Future of Paris" article for Atlantic Monthly. 20 Feb. 1943
  - Correspondence with French city planners.1930s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: City Planning: San Francisco and Palo Alto.1950s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: City Planning: San Francisco and Palo Alto.1949-1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: City Planning: San Francisco and Palo Alto. 1950s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: City Planning: San Francisco and Palo Alto.1950s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - City Planning: Carbons of book reviews by ALG. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - City Planning: Carbons of book reviews by ALG. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - City Planning: Carbons of book reviews by ALG. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - City Planning: Carbons of book reviews by ALG. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Book Reviews
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Carbons of published book reviews. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stanford Review. March 1960. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series V: Published copies and reprints of many of the articles in Series I. (Accession # 83-100)
  - -"Art for Art's Sake." In Southwest Review, Summer 1953. 3 copies. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - -"Can it be world democracy?" In Antioch Winter 1944-45 Review. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - - "Capitalism --- Doctrine, Myth or Style?" In Southwest Review, Vol. XXIV, no. 1 Oct. 1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - - "The Quick and the Dead 'English' or 'Literature'?" Chap book published by the College English Association, Univ. of Massachusetts. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - - Supplement to The CEA Critic, Col XII, No. 2, Feb. 1951-2 copies. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - - "Europe Free and United" Publisher's catalog entry. Stanford Univ. Press, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - - "Fossils, Classics, and Presences." In Southwest Summer 1957 Review, Summer 1957. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - - "The Growth of the Historical Spirit." In Stanford Studies in Language and Literature, 1941. 5 copies (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - - "Home Language, Official Language, Culture Language." In International Language Review. July-Sept. 1958 3 copies. Includes advertisement for ALG's Fossils and Presences. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - - "How will history judge De Gaulle?" In Best Articles & Stories, April 1960. Originally published in Southwest Review. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - - "Honoré de Balzac et la Comédie Humaine" 3 public lectures published by The Rice Institue. Rice Institute Pamphlet, Vol. X, No. 2, Apr. 1923. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - - "In Memoriam Albert Leon Guerard 1880-1959." In International Language Review. Jan-Mar 1960 3 copies. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - - "International Language and National Cultures." In The American Scholar, Spring 1941. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - - "The International Language Problem Today." No publication information. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - - "Knowledge and Wisdom - Dr. Albert Guérard's last manuscript." In The Stanford Review, Feb. 1960. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - - "Mémorial de Saint-Cloud 1960." Obituary notice in alumni bulletin, pp. 38-40. 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - - Andrew Forest Muir. "Murder on Madison Avenue, the Rice case revisited." In Southwest Review, Winter 1959. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - - "Must de Gaulle Fail?" In Southwest Review, Autumn 1959. 3 copies (2 entire issues, 1 reprint) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "The New Quarrel of the Ancients and the Moderns." In University of California Chronicle, July 1925. 3 copies. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - - "Notes on Mario Pei - one language for the world and how to achieve it." In International Language Review, Apr.-June 1958. 3 copies (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - - "Preliminary Draft of a World Constitution." ALG among writers and signers. Common Cause, a monthly report of the committee to frame a world constitution. March 1948. 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - - "The Quest of Excellence, a humanistic utopia." In The American Scholar. Vol. 29, no. 1, Winter 1959-60. 2 reprints, 2 entire issues (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - - "Ramblings of a Cheerful Ghost." Reminiscences of Stanford, 1907-1958. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - - "Ten Levels of Language." In The American Scholar, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - - "To My Unknown Friends in India." In The Aryan Path, Feb. 1958. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - - Review for The Literary Works of Count de Gobineau, A.H. Rowbotham, 1929. In The University of California Chronicle, April 1930, pp. 234-35. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - - "To My African Friends." In The Atlantic, Feb. 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)